<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>Tom Hazledine</title>
<description>The personal web-hub for Tom Hazledine</description>
<link></link>
<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
<title>Simple Is Hard</title>
<description>&lt;h3&gt;“Simplify, simplfy!” we’re often told. Your service isn’t appealing to your customers? The answer’s simple: simplify! Your song isn’t connecting with your fanbase? Simplify! You aren’t shifting as many units as Apple? Simplify! It’s an easy mantra to mock, and even easier to swallow hook, line, and sinker. We need to make the distinction between ‘simple’ and ‘simplistic’.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, it often seems that the outlets with the most simplistic messages to get across are the ones most overrun by crowded, cluttered, un-navigable interfaces. If what you’re saying has value, you don’t need the kitchen sink to help you say it. But what do you need? And how much can you afford to throw out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Only keep what you need.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to think of simplifying a design as merely stripping away layers of visual ornamentation, but true simplicity comes more from the &lt;em&gt;user experience&lt;/em&gt; than the look of the thing. Hiding an unsightly menu behind a &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobile.smashingmagazine.com/2012/10/08/the-semantic-responsive-design-navicon/&quot;&gt;hamburger icon&lt;/a&gt; is an easy way to de-clutter an app’s interface, to be sure, but does that count as simplification? All that’s really achieved is to force the user to make an extra click when they want to navigate somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearing away useless clutter is generally a good tactic, but there’s a distinct difference between &lt;em&gt;simplifying&lt;/em&gt; a product and merely making it’s function more obtuse. Is one button with five functions really better than five buttons that each do one task? Is an aesthetically-pure minimalist interface really ideal if you then need to teach every new user how it works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any task worth doing, there are many levels of nuance to simplification. It takes judgement; an assessment of what functions are important to your product, your app, your idea. Strip away anything extraneous and put anything the user needs front-and-centre, but don’t confuse the two or you’ll live to regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;This website is all about words.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The page you’re reading now went through many iterations before settling on the look you see today. Early drafts were swamped with full-page background images and clever CSS3 animation effects, but no matter how fancy I got with the coding these early designs never felt quite right. Then I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;http://justinjackson.ca/words.html&quot;&gt;Justin Jackson’s inspired ‘This Is A Web Page’ anticle&lt;/a&gt; and was reminded that what was important for this site was the words themselves. It goes deeper than that, even: what’s important to this site is the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt;. It could be read aloud by a screen-reader, translated into sign-language, even transmitted telepathically for all I care. As long as the message can be absorbed, this page will have done it’s job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I was doing with my early designs was trying to build a ‘great website’, when what I should really have been focusing on was building a great content delivery system. It seems video is the &lt;em&gt;de rigueur&lt;/em&gt; medium for getting messages across quickly, and for a while I did toy with the idea of making this page into a vlog, but ultimately words are purer. Video is harder to create than written content, and would skew the message with all the baggage brought along by seeing my face (beautiful) or hearing my accent (perfectly inflected Queen’s English). With the written word I have more chance of capturing the ‘white heat of inspiration’ and of being able to communicate my thoughts clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why use any styling at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why not go all-out and strip out all the styling from this page completely? Properly written semantic HTML is nothing &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; content, so surely stripping away everything else would be the most efficient way to get the message across? Firstly, because raw HTML looks scary; my first instinct upon seeing any is to assume the website’s broken. Even though it’s nothing but content, to untrained eyes it looks techy, involved, &lt;em&gt;intimidating&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s often said that &lt;a href=&quot;http://alistapart.com/article/on-web-typography#section3&quot;&gt;we read best what we read most&lt;/a&gt;, and my target demographic reads books. Books are fantastically efficient, and the best ones are things of beauty that wrap their content in a nourishing blanket of aesthetic proportions and finely-wrought typefaces. Given how many books I own solely on the topic of type design and typography, I can’t stand idly by and leave my content at the mercy of the ‘web-safe’ default fonts. I have to believe that good typography and good design makes the reading experience better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Simple doesn’t have to be ugly.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems obvious, but websites &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; have a lot to learn from books. Just because we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; swamp everything in technical wizardry doesn’t mean we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;, but it equally doesn’t mean we should abandon design altogether. ‘Simple’ doesn’t (and &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt;) mean ‘ugly’, and the simple act of thinking about line-lengths and visual hierarchies can turn an indigestible splurge of HTML into something readable, and in the right hands even something beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the right balance between visual simplicity, simplicity of interaction and a pleasing aesthetic is really tough, and I’ll be the first to admit I’ve still a long way to go. But at least now I’m pointing in the right direction; simple is important, simple is necessary, and simple is really hard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>/simple-is-hard</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">/simple-is-hard</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Getting Things Done</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;﻿—
layout: post
title: “Get Things Done”
excerpt: How my Bullet Journal has revolutionized my workflow.
comments: true
—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It amazes me that the &lt;em&gt;Get Things Done&lt;/em&gt; concept has sprung up an entire community, even an entire &lt;em&gt;industry&lt;/em&gt;. In what seems like an immediately defeatist manner, there are books and books and books on GTD (as the cool kids call it) and any number of websites devoted to the topic. As someone who will happily obsess over the finest minutiae of something for ages before actually &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; anything, this brand of procrastinating about avoiding procrastinating really hits me where I live.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, though, it seems that all the hours I’ve spent reading about productivity-hacks weren’t wasted after all; my current system finds me being &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; efficient and productive than I’ve ever been before. At the hub of my new-found Get Things Done momentum lies my Bullet Journal. Devised by the inspired Brooklynite &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rydercarroll.com/&quot;&gt;Ryder Carrol&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&quot;&gt;Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt; is at its heart a seemingly-simple method of writing out a ‘to-do’ list using nothing more than a pen and a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;I don’t think the journal is &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; responsible for my productivity upswing.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of a disclaimer, making the switch to a Bullet Journal workflow wasn’t the only change I’ve made recently. A few months ago I quit my day-job and struck out on my own; an intrepid freelancer &lt;em&gt;cum&lt;/em&gt; entrepreneur bound for riches and glory! So now that any-and-all money that I make is directly proportional to how much work I do, it’ll come as no surprise that I’m working harder and longer than ever before (and would be with or without the Bullet Journal).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>/getting-things-done</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">/getting-things-done</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>I Hate Driving</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Driving lessons suck. They’re expensive and I hate them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>/i-hate-driving</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">/i-hate-driving</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>