<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>Tom Hazledine</title>
<description>The personal web-hub for Tom Hazledine</description>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com</link>
<atom:link href="http://tomhazledine.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
<title>Notes from ThinkMonk: Day One</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;ThingMonk styles itself as a conference “for developers, designers, data wranglers and decision-makers that want to turn ideas and concepts into industrial scale systems”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was there with my web-developer hat on, but was keeping my eyes peeled for hints at the future of business-tech in general. I’m already deeply embedded in data-visualisation and dynamic analytics, but eager to connect my digital skills to a hardware framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Day One&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bullet-Proof &amp;amp; Profitable Things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu guru and part-time space tourist &lt;a href=&quot;http://canonical.com/&quot;&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/a&gt; made for a high-profile, big-picture opening speaker. It was interesting to hear that his idea of “scale” was not massive super-computers costing exorbitant amounts of money, but rather lots and lots of cheap, tiny micro-computers all working in unison over a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It takes five to ten years to make an overnight success, and &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; is the time to be getting deep into IoT. Wait 12 months and the train will have left the station.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real disruption comes from riding a wave of change, and the disaggregation and componentisation we’re seeing in the IoT sphere at the moment will inevitably lead to the “hockey stick” graph of innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data can be a liability - you must have a responsible security strategy when handling lots of data. One mistake or hack can cripple a big-data company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next version of Ubuntu will be highly modular. Apps will be isolated and contained, and will each have a predefined area they can write to. This allows for robust version control across the system, and no more fear when updating the OS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “Internet of Toys” is going to be more influential than people realise. It’s easier to innovate with things that won’t kill people. Long-term projects will have to use standards already set by short-term projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Coherent UX for Distributed Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User-experience expert &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.designingconnectedproducts.com/&quot;&gt;Claire Rowland&lt;/a&gt; had some fascinating insights into the challenges of managing UX in a world of connected “things”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We don’t expect “things” to behave like the internet. Light bulbs shouldn’t “buffer”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interfaces (if they are honest) should introduce the concept of failure to users. Don’t fake success when a user clicks a button in a low-connectivity area: show in interstitial “loading” state wherever possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You often have to choose between fuzzy-and-current or accurate-but-old. A cat-tracker can either say “Mrs. Tibbles was at this exact location 3 hours ago” or “Mrs. Tibbles is somewhere within this range right now”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linking physical and digital interfaces takes special thought. A traditional dimmer-switch always knows it’s ‘state’, where as a remotely-controlled version has to account for the fact that the ‘state’ of the bulb might have changed since it last checked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;From 2 to 2 billion: How to Design for Scale.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Winslet &amp;amp; Sophie Riches from IBM presented us with the “Seven Deadly Sins for Design of IoT”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greed: designing for yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Envy: being a copycat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gluttony: focusing on features &amp;amp; functions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrath: assuming your users know what IoT is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lust: IoT for the sake of it, without any real ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pride: don’t over-complicate and don’t over-simplify. IBM use a strategy they call “Progressive Disclosure”: where an interface reveals deeper levels of detail as a user interacts with it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sloth: assuming users have ∞ patience or care about you/your product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hacking NFC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Ludlum from &lt;a href=&quot;http://moo.com/&quot;&gt;Moo&lt;/a&gt; gave (with a little help from colleague Kai Turner) one of the more engaging and tech-focused presentations of the event. The team at Moo have (after considerable time spent in R&amp;amp;D) figured out how to print NFC chips into business cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every attendee at the conference was given a Moo business card on arrival, which was embedded with an NFC chip with tokens for free coffee and beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For NFC to work, you need a chip and an antenna. The chip is tiny – literally mm across – and the antenna gets printed between to laminated sheets of paper using conductive silver ink. This means the finished business card looks and feels just like a regular card - after all, it’s still mostly just card and ink.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To build a reader, all you need is a “smarter” chip, an antenna, and a power source. Android phones have the ability to be NFC readers, but IOS ones do not.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;nfcpy&lt;/code&gt; is the Python library for NFC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cards can store a variety of MIME-type information (webpages, lat. &amp;amp; lng. data, etc) but URLs are the most versatile (and can be re-purposed without reprogramming the card itself).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security is still ongoing project, and the Moo team would welcome any insights or help in that area that the developer community can provide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Things Network: London&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Hill, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://opentrv.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Open TRV&lt;/a&gt; (a company that makes smart Thermostatic Radiator Valves) got the short-straw: his talk was right before lunch, and therefore had to be shortened because the conf. was running over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thethingsnetwork.org/&quot;&gt;The Things Network&lt;/a&gt; is a low-power, wide-area network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crowdsourced a complete city-wide IoT data network in Amsterdam.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launching the network in cities across the world. London had its network launched this month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Powered by gateways installed on roofs of businesses, accessible to all. ($1000 - $1500 per gateway).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Data Gravity &amp;amp; Time-series&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave McCrory, allegedly famous for for coining the term “data gravity”, delivered an engaging talk with a charming hand-drawn slide-deck. He touched briefly on how data != information, but his main point was that dealing with time (in an IoT setting) is important but very, very hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Gravity: data has a ‘weight’ and can be hard to deal with. Some datasets might take 40 years to even upload, let alone process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; is just data. &lt;code&gt;0°C&lt;/code&gt; is data with context. &lt;code&gt;0°C in London today&lt;/code&gt; is information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you are working with real-time analytics, how do you deal with that data? System clocks become important - do you trust your machine, your cloud server, or the machine in the field?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you deliver a constant stream of data? Sometimes it might be better to time-stamp it and package it up, then send packets of data at regular intervals. That leads to less chance of drops in connection causing data loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Secret Life of Buildings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to head Yodit Stanton’s insights into working with “connected“ buildings, particularly some of the pitfalls and unexpected issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Her company &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opensensors.io/&quot;&gt;opensensors.io&lt;/a&gt; deals with commercial spaces with pre-existing Building Management Systems (BMSs).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automation in a machine-to-machine sense (M2M) has been around for years: office lights that turn on when you enter the room, automatic doors, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning about a building’s ‘health’ in the form of lighting-levels, environmental factors, footfall, etc. can give you insight into employee absenteeism, efficiency of your workforce, and on and on…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average cost of one desk in London is £12k p.a. Small percentage increases in efficiency can reap big rewards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legacy protocols (&lt;code&gt;bacnet&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dali&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;modbus&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;knx&lt;/code&gt;) are building-data standards and will be around for a while. Contracts are typically 15-20 years long, and cost between £50k and £200k. They won’t be thrown out anytime soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They lock down their data too much. None of those services have an API.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Source integrations are more sustainable and easier to manage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t use WiFi - there are “edge dependencies” on people (in one example, an office manager unplugged the wi-fi router every night!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It’s none of your effing business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The award for most curmudgeonly speaker at the event goes to Boris Adryan (according to ThingMonk host James Governor). Boris devoted a large portion of his talk to dissecting an article depicting a &lt;a href=&quot;http://knowledge.openboxsoftware.com/blog/the-evolution-of-business-intelligence&quot;&gt;near-future IoT-fueled wakeup routine&lt;/a&gt;. The post is well-worth a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also touched on machine learning, and I started craving a cup of tea and took fewer notes… In short, we need our systems to be smart because people instinctively lack an understanding of statistical p-values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Things, People, and Beer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craig Cmehil, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://go.sap.com/uk/index.html&quot;&gt;SAP&lt;/a&gt;, subtitled his talk “voice as an alternative user interface for analytics”. He gave a demonstration of the voice-activated Amazon Echo, essentially a programmable Siri in a large box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He ran a mini competition, too, where he gave away an Echo (not yet available in Europe) which involved some live-coding: always a brave mood in a live presentation…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;IoT Device Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juan Perez (from Microsoft) said some stuff about Azure (a new MS Cloud platform or something-or-other). I may have slept through this one…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Welcome to the Conversation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official father of the term “Silicon Roundabout”, Matt Biddulph, closed day one with a talk about how ‘conversation’ can help solve some of the main issues with many IoT devices. He was very coy about his new venture, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thington.com/&quot;&gt;Thington&lt;/a&gt;, but hinted that it will be using this concept of conversation in conjunction with the “social graph” when it launches in early 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional light-bulbs are an interface an messaging bus. A light-switch is a state messaging transport. Adding connectivity to a bulb (&lt;em&gt;a la&lt;/em&gt; Philips Hue) adds issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;latency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consensus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an ‘old’ scholarly article that outlines the 8 fallacies of distributed computing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The network is reliable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latency is zero.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bandwidth is infinite.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The network is secure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Topology doesn’t change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is one administrator.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transport cost is zero.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The network is homogeneous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt’s “New fallacies of Distributes &lt;em&gt;Services&lt;/em&gt;”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Devices are powered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Devices are reachable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Devices stay in one place.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Messages can be trusted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Causality is unambiguous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All device state is known.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is one clock.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we solve these issues? Simple: a conversation. If the devices can ‘talk’ to one-another, they can iron out inconsistencies and neutralize many of the problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At somepoint in the next week or so (mid-late Dec 2015) I’ll post my notes from day 2 of ThingMonk. I’ll add the link here, but if you’re really desparate not to miss out, drop me a line (tom@tomhazledine.com) and I’ll add you to the slowly-growing list of people who I’ll email when I’ve published the notes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/thingmonk-day-one</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/thingmonk-day-one</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Getting started with inline SVG icons</title>
<description>&lt;!--![png – font character – svg](/)
with scale-slider?--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should all know by now that using raster images for icons is a bad idea. Limiting ourselves to one set resolution is not how we work in a multi-device ecosystem. It’s not responsive, it’s not performant, it’s not nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a while it seemed that Icon Fonts were the answer. They’re vector based and therefore resolution-independent. You can style them with CSS. They have smaller filesizes than .JPGs or .PNGs, so they improve a site’s performance. A fontfile is one asset to download (more http requests = poorer site performance), so we don’t need to mess around with image sprites any more. And on top of all that, iconfont creation can be easily automated with your task-runner of choice: simply drop your icon .SVGs into a folder and you’re good to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/* Calling an iconfont icon as a pseudo element within CSS. */
.elementName:before {
    font-family:'iconfont';
	content: &quot;\e001&quot;; // The unicode value of the font character you want.
	color: #000; // The icon is text, so you can style it using regular CSS
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;If it ain’t broke, why fix it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately the winds of change have been blowing. Fewer and fewer big-name sites are using iconfonts, and more and more are publicly coming out in favour of inline SVGs. At first I was sceptical: “that problem’s already been solved”, I thought. Actually inlining raw SVG code into a site seemed overly complicated, and harder to maintain and automate than an iconfont setup. But was it? And were iconfonts as great as they first appeared?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;When iconfonts fail, things get weird.&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes there’s no telling what crazy character a browser will display in place of an icon that hasn’t loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;There are inexplicable rendering inconsistencies.&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Firefox in particular seemed, like an overly generous grandparent, determined to fatten my icons up. Faux-bold on regular fonts is ugly and annoying, but when it happens to brand assets like icons it’s excruciating (and something clients &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; pick up on).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Automation isn’t so seamless after all.&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Oh hey, my &lt;code&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt; keeps failing. I wonder what the problem is: oh yeah, my &lt;code&gt;gulp-iconfont&lt;/code&gt; is throwing errors all up in my grill. Again. #facepalm&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, pure SVG is a much more consistent format. I’ve been using SVGs within &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags since 2006, and I’ve never had any trouble with setting SVGs as CSS background images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/* SVG CSS background-image. */
.elementName {
    height:1em;
    width:1em;
    background-image: url(path/to/icon.png); // Fallback for browsers that don't like SVG.
    background-image: url(path/to/icon.svg);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt; solution is to just use SVGs like that: set them with CSS or use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements. That gives you scaleable vector graphics that work well in most environments. The trouble is, you’re loading in a new file for every icon. Every icon would represent another HTTP request to the server, and would be a performance nightmare. No matter how “squishy” your design, if your site is slow to load it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; “Responsive”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re back to the same multiple-requests problem we had in the bad old days of raster iconography. The answer back then was to use image sprites. Concatenate all the icons into one file, load them all with just one HTTP request, and use CSS to crop the image when you want to display a particular icon. It turns out we can do that with SVG too, except now we can do it better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Inline SVG Sprites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVGs are made of paths – collections of co-ordinates that describe the individual vectors of the image. Open an SVG in your favourite text editor and you can see those paths. What’s more, you can add classes and IDs to them. Even more mindblowing: if you wrap the individual paths in a &lt;code&gt;symbol&lt;/code&gt; tag you can combine multiple images into a single SVG file, and selectively pull them out using their IDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Load the SVG file into your document... --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;symbol viewBox=&quot;0 0 10 10&quot; id=&quot;iconID&quot;&amp;gt;
		&amp;lt;path d=&quot;{ vector data }&quot;/&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;/symbol&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/svg&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;!-- ...and then 'use' a specific icon --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;svg class=&quot;icon&quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#iconID&quot;/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/svg&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might be thinking that this all looks like a whole lot of work, and you’d be right. Making sprites by hand sucks. Thankfully the arrow of progress is on our side. We may not have jetpacks and flying cars yet, but we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have task runners. I used to use Grunt, but now I use Gulp (being a JS nerd, I find the syntax easier to follow) and there are SVG spriting plugins for both of them. I use &lt;code&gt;gulp-svg-sprite&lt;/code&gt;, and so far it’s worked like a charm (so far I’ve put it to work on a half-dozen private projects and a couple of client sites). In fact, it’s proving to be much more reliable than any of the Gulp plugins for iconfonts ever were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a bit of configuring to get the drop-an-icon-into-a-folder-and-let-Gulp-do-the-rest workflow I’d maintained with iconfonts, but as long as you remember to specify that you want a &lt;code&gt;symbol&lt;/code&gt; based sprite, you can’t go too wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// My Gulp config
var svgConfig = {
    shape : {
        dimension : { // Set maximum dimensions
            maxWidth : 32,
            maxHeight : 32
        }
    },
    mode : {
        symbol : true // Activate the «symbol» mode
    }
};
// The task itself
gulp.task('svg',function(){
    return gulp.src('_uncompressed/icons/**/*.svg')
        .pipe(svgSprite(svgConfig))
        .pipe(gulp.dest('_includes'));
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Inline SVG in Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This site is built using the static-site generator Jekyll. Transferring this site’s (admittedly meagre) icon set from an iconfont to an inline SVG sprite couldn’t have been easier. Make sure your task-runner outputs your sprite into Jekyll’s &lt;code&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt; directory and you can pull in your sprite with a simple &lt;code&gt;{% include /symbol/svg/sprite.symbol.svg %}&lt;/code&gt;. And because Jekyll compiles &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; deployment, you don’t even have to make a single HTTP request to get your icons: it’s all truly inline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Inline SVG in Wordpress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll’s all well and good if your clients are happy with working in code and using the command line to update their site. Sadly the world hardly ever makes things &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; easy for us. Wordpress sites don’t have the advantage of being compiled before deployment, which means we need to use PHP to include the sprite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Including an automatically generated SVG sprite using PHP is a little trickier than it first appears. &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?php include_once(&quot;path/to/svg/sprite.svg&quot;); ?&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; would seem like the obvious solution, but all that will give you is a face full of errors (if you’ve got &lt;code&gt;WP_DEBUG&lt;/code&gt; set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;). It turns out the issue is with the XML and &lt;code&gt;DOCTYPE&lt;/code&gt; added to the sprite by the gulp task, and the trick is to use &lt;code&gt;file_get_contents()&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;include_once()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;SVG &amp;amp; CSS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Styling the icons had a couple of little hurdles that I wasn’t expecting. One of the joys of iconfonts was how easy they were to manipulate with CSS, and that’s a feature that SVG sprites were promising too. Instead of &lt;code&gt;color: #000;&lt;/code&gt; we use &lt;code&gt;fill: #000;&lt;/code&gt; but, as with all CSS, watch out for specificity! If the paths themselves have explicit fills and strokes defined, then you won’t be able to override them with external CSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my legacy icons have in-built colours, and going through and stripping them out would be a real pain. Thankfully my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/enshrined&quot;&gt;Daryll&lt;/a&gt; was on hand to build me a tidy RegEx to programatically strip out any rogue fills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?php
// Save the SVG file in a variable...
$rawSVG = file_get_contents(get_template_directory_uri() . &quot;/path/to/svg/sprite.svg&quot;);
// ...then filter out any fills.
echo preg_replace( '/fill=(&quot;|\')(#)?([a-fA-F0-9]*)(&quot;|\')/i', '', $rawSVG )
?&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m using Jekyll I still have to manually manage explicit in-file styling, but Jekyll projects tend to require a more fine-grained approach anyway. Another Big Win for CSS styling and SVGs comes from being able to add classes and IDs to specific paths &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; individual icons. This provides us with the hooks we need to style (and animate and manipulate) almost every aspect of an icon discretely. Iconfonts were limited to one flat colour, but with SVG sprites we can colour every shape in an icon differently (should we need to).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time I was very skeptical of using inline SVG for icon sets, primarily because of the perceived effort it would take to set up such a system. I’m happy to report that SVG sprites are considerably easier to get started with than I’d ever thought. I can’t imagine ever using an iconfont again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/inline-svg-icons</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/inline-svg-icons</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Inspirational Web People</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;There’s an &lt;a href=&quot;http://boagworld.com/season/10/episode/1007/&quot;&gt;episode of the Boagworld podcast&lt;/a&gt; where Marcus and Paul list the ten ‘web people’ they’ve found most &lt;em&gt;inspiring&lt;/em&gt;. This has in turn inspired &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; to publish my own list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web-creators community is packed with generous people willing to share their insights and experiences. Through blog posts and podcasts, conference talks and tutorials, these people have had a direct impact on my outlook and my career choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;01: &lt;a href=&quot;http://stevenlovegrove.com/&quot;&gt;Steve Lovegrove&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience everyone has that one person that inspired them when they were just starting out. For some it’s a teacher, or someone who gave them their first break, or a professional who mentored them. For me, it was my friend Steve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve’s always been miles ahead of me in intellect and ability, and most of what he tried to teach me went straight over my head. But even so, he was willing to let me spend hours peering over his shoulder while he coded. And because we would also talk through what he was working on, some of it rubbed off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve taught me just enough to be dangerous; just enough to get something on the web and see how good it felt. He’s long since left the web behind to do ‘real’ science, but having a patient and generous friend like Steve was probably the single biggest factor in shaping the direction my career has taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;02: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/chriscoyier&quot;&gt;Chris Coyier&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/davatron5000&quot;&gt;Dave Rupert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who’s ever Googled a CCS question has probably benefited from Chris’ sterling work on his website &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/&quot;&gt;CSS Tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s his video tutorials (on Lynda.com and the “Lodge” section of his own website) that have impacted my world the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His approach of &lt;em&gt;getting-it-wrong-on-camera-and-then-fixing-it-(probably)&lt;/em&gt; was a welcome break from other more sanitised tutorials. Not everything installs perfectly the first time, and &lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; is immune from typos.  Seeing how professionals deal with these problems is almost as useful as the main focus of the lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris also does sterling work in the podcast field with his partner in crime Dave Rupert. If you’re not entertained by the combination of in-depth Q-and-A, stupid sound effects, and friendly banter that they put out in the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shoptalkshow.com/&quot;&gt;Shop Talk Show&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, then you’re probably not interested in front-end development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, their mantra is probably the single most useful bit of advice any web professional can give:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just. Build. Websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;03: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/brad_frost&quot;&gt;Brad Frost&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m never more aware of (or excited by) the unique nature of designing for the web than when I listen to Brad Frost. If every colleague and every client could take the time to &lt;a href=&quot;http://bradfrostweb.com/blog/&quot;&gt;read his blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nE0CRMm59BY&quot;&gt;watch his talks&lt;/a&gt;, the standard of our work and the quality of our work-lives would raise ten-fold across the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of designing ‘paintings of websites’ (a.k.a. PSD mockups) is completely outdated; we can’t just design for one ideal viewport size, or two, or ten, or a hundred. “Atomic Design” might sound like a buzz word, but the principles are applicable to all web work. The basic concept of designing components first and pages last is quite simply How It Should Be Done Now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;04: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/markbrickey&quot;&gt;Mark Brickey&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/thejamesflames&quot;&gt;James Flames&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/DeliciousDL&quot;&gt;Billy Bauman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love to hear people talking candidly and in-depth about fields they are experts in. It almost doesn’t matter what the topic is (which is one of the reasons I love Radio 4’s &lt;em&gt;In Our Time&lt;/em&gt; so much), but when the topic is illustration I love it even more. The &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aidpodcast.com/&quot;&gt;Adventures In Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; podcast is irreverent and unhinged, but always honest and informative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They always have good guests, but more importantly Mark, Billy and James know what to do with them. They trigger interesting and inspirational discussion, no matter who the guest is. The resulting interviews are often challenging, often controversial, and always riveting listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason I like AID so much is that team aren’t ashamed of making a living: this is a podcast about the &lt;strong&gt;business&lt;/strong&gt; of design. It just so happens that the design field they work in is the super-cool one of gig posters and illustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; 05: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/monteiro&quot;&gt;Mike Monteiro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone working in the world of design who deals with clients should watch Mike’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/22053820&quot;&gt;F*ck You. Pay Me.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; talk. He explains why it’s important to take yourself and your business seriously, and even brings his lawyer on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His book, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abookapart.com/products/design-is-a-job&quot;&gt;Design Is a Job&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, is less caustic, but just as inspiring. His book, Design Is a Job, is less caustic, but just as inspiring. Neither the book nor the talk are rants against stupid clients (well, maybe a little…). They focus instead on building &lt;strong&gt;productive&lt;/strong&gt; client relationships where no-one is taken advantage of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to admit that sometimes a problem doesn’t stem from the client but from yourself. Even so, having that in the back of my mind has often saved my freelancing-bacon. Following Mike’s advice has often turned tricky clients into excellent ones. For all his acetic bluster, Mike’s core message is simple; be friendly and use common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;06: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/jessicahische&quot;&gt;Jessica Hische&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jessica is a letterer, and all her work is stunning. Before I was aware of her, I didn’t even know ‘lettering’ was an actual job that you could do. Back in the day, Jessica was a jack-of-all-trades (like many of us), but she realised that You Get The Work You Show. She filled her portfolio with self-initiated lettering work, and was soon able to specialise professionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Art directors (and all clients, in fact) aren’t blinkered and lacking in imagination. With so much talent out there, they can find someone with &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the right experience and demonstrable expertise. If you think lettering is your strongest skill but stack your portfolio with e-commerce websites, guess what kind of work you’re more likely to be hired for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to specialise in something, you have to get off the mat and &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; it. Don’t wait for the “dream commission” to come walking through the door; get out there and chase it down. Jessica makes her own luck, and makes me think I might be able to make my own, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;07: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/TrentWalton&quot;&gt;Trent Walton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only so many ways to present seriffed text on a light background, but somehow Trent manages to make &lt;a href=&quot;http://trentwalton.com/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt; look nicer than everyone else’s. His art-directed posts (each with their own custom styling) are a benchmark for bloggers everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat annoyingly, what he writes about is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; several orders of magnitude better than anything I could manage. I don’t know if he became so respected by writing well about “big picture” subjects or whether he writes well &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; he’s so respected, but either way, respected he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His posts come fairly infrequently, but when they do they’re invariably beautiful &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;08: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/benschwarz&quot;&gt;Ben Schwarz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task runners (like Grunt and Gulp) have revolutionised my workflow over the past year. Grunt trickled into my sphere of awareness over a period of months, much like SASS. SASS I adopted more by osmosis than through any deliberate choice, but I can pin-point my adoption of Grunt to one specific incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben has made a &lt;a href=&quot;http://benschwarz.github.io/gallery-css/&quot;&gt;fantastic CSS-only Slider&lt;/a&gt;, and I bought his accompanying screecast tutorial. It might be the best £10 I’ve ever spent. The video explains his intricate SASS, but also walks through a Grunt installation and shows how useful it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to that point, I was aware of Grunt but didn’t understand it or see the point of it. To see someone as consummately professional as Ben using it and extolling its virtues sealed the deal. I’ve since switched from Grunt to Gulp, but using &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; task runner at all has been the real quantum leap for my workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;09: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/seanuk&quot;&gt;Sean Johnson&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/liz_e&quot;&gt;Liz Elcoate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quitting a job to go freelance is a daunting proposition. Making the leap myself, I found comfort in the curious trend for freelance-web-folk-focused podcasts. There are plenty of great offerings out there, but by far the most relevant to my past situation was &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thefreelanceweb.com/&quot;&gt;The Freelance Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liz and Sean aren’t afraid to deep-dive into the details of running a web business; both the good parts and the bad. Their advice is useful &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; reassuring, and the fact that they talk about specifics makes it all the more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve since moved from freelancing to an agency position, but I still enjoy &lt;em&gt;The Freelance Web&lt;/em&gt;. The willingness to share experiences and knowledge is one of the best characteristics of the web community. It’s one I find it hard to believe any other industry could match, and Liz and Sean are true embodiments of that generous spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;10: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/enshrined&quot;&gt;Daryll Doyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a day-to-day basis, by far my biggest inspiration is my team mate, Daryll. He’s very much from the school of thought that says “if you’re not moving forwards, you’re moving backwards”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much constantly, Daryll is showing me some new tool he’s discovered, technique he’s mastered, or framework he’s learnt. His dedication to self-improvement is nothing short of inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a couple of the people on this list IRL, and a couple more I’d class as ‘digital acquaintances’, but most are just web personalities who’s work, public speaking, or blogging has taught me something new, steered me when my course has wandered, opened my eyes to new ways of thinking, or just been inspiring in some more ineffable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like this are what makes the web such a fantastic industry to be a part of, and I owe them all a debt of gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/inspiring-web-people</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/inspiring-web-people</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Top ten ways to progress.</title>
<description>&lt;h2&gt;The top ten ways to get better at your chosen skill:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Practice [repeat, x10]&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
    var postsList = [];
    var currentPost = 0;

    

        postsList[0] = [];
        
        postsList[0][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/thingmonk-day-one&quot;;
        postsList[0][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Notes from ThinkMonk: Day One&quot;;

        

    

        postsList[1] = [];
        
        postsList[1][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/inline-svg-icons&quot;;
        postsList[1][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Getting started with inline SVG icons&quot;;

        

    

        postsList[2] = [];
        
        postsList[2][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/inspiring-web-people&quot;;
        postsList[2][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Inspirational Web People&quot;;

        

    

        postsList[3] = [];
        
        postsList[3][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/top-ten-ways-to-get-better-at-something&quot;;
        postsList[3][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Top ten ways to progress.&quot;;

        
            var currentPost = 3;
        

    

        postsList[4] = [];
        
        postsList[4][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/fullpage-screenshots-in-firefox&quot;;
        postsList[4][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Fullpage screenshots in Firefox.&quot;;

        

    

        postsList[5] = [];
        
        postsList[5][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/futura-for-the-win&quot;;
        postsList[5][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Futura for the win.&quot;;

        

    

        postsList[6] = [];
        
        postsList[6][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/simple-is-hard&quot;;
        postsList[6][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;Simple is hard&quot;;

        

    

        postsList[7] = [];
        
        postsList[7][&quot;url&quot;] = &quot;/bullet-journal-workflow&quot;;
        postsList[7][&quot;title&quot;] = &quot;A bullet-journal workflow&quot;;

        

    
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;nav id=&quot;nextPrevWrapper&quot; class=&quot;nav-outer clearfix&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;nextBox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;prevBox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/top-ten-ways-to-get-better-at-something</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/top-ten-ways-to-get-better-at-something</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Fullpage screenshots in Firefox.</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Every now and then I need to take a screenshot of an entire webpage, gnerally to use in my &lt;a href=&quot;/portfolio&quot;&gt;portfolio&lt;/a&gt;. Manually positioning the cursor for a &lt;code&gt;cmd shift 4&lt;/code&gt; screenshot (on a Mac) feels a little imprecise for my tastes, and I want to capture the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; of a site, not just the area visible in the viewport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the browser extensions I tried turned out a little buggy. Areas of the page would be repeated, like a visual interpretation of a CD skipping, or fonts would render strangely, as if they’d been run through an IE8 simulator or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I stumbled upon this neat little trick. Sadly it doesn’t help me get girls or lose weight like all the “one weird trick” pop-up ads keep promising me, but it does mean I can take a screenshot of an entire webpage using one line of code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The answer!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to the page you want to shoot and open up Firefox’s Developer Tools command line using &lt;code&gt;shift f2&lt;/code&gt; (Mac users might need to remember to press &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; as well, if their keyboard rebinds &lt;code&gt;f2&lt;/code&gt; to increase the monitor’s brightness). Then all you need to do is type the following line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;screenshot --fullpage YourFileNameHere
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And voilà! A screenshot has been taken of the current page in its entirety – not just the visible area! If you’re super lazy, you can even leave off the file name; Firefox will just use the current date and time to save the image under.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found I needed to crop off a sliver of transparency on the right hand side when I opened the shots up in Photoshop, but that’s a small price to pay for the time saved not having to stitch together various peepshow-views of a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;See it in action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of the screenshots I took using this method over on my portfolio page. The ‘phone’ view of the &lt;a href=&quot;/atlantic-brewery&quot;&gt;Atlantic Brewery&lt;/a&gt; page is particularly long and thin – an image I’d have struggled to create using any other method.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/fullpage-screenshots-in-firefox</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/fullpage-screenshots-in-firefox</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Futura for the win.</title>
<description>&lt;p class=&quot;addendum&quot;&gt;This post was written in 2014. As you’ve no doubt already noticed, I’ve moved on from Futura as the typeface for this site. &lt;!--Read about why I made the switch [here](/)--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial ‘Contemporary Drop Cap’ concept was much more florid and overtly ornamental than what you see today (as of April 2014). I burnt through many drafts experimenting with ornate serif fonts before I finally remembered that what I was trying to build was a &lt;strong&gt;portfolio&lt;/strong&gt;; a neutral backdrop for my designs, not something that would distract from the work on show. In short, I needed a sans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;shadowImg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/articleImages/futuraDropcap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Futura Dropcap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Neutral doesn’t mean flavourless.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the most generic-seeming typefaces have their own distinct flavour, as my Helvetica-fuelled “Hey look! I just discovered Swiss Design” phase will attest (now commonly known as my “God-awful Superdry Period”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve developed a deep and abiding love for a perfectly circular “o”, so when choosing a sans I normally start with the geometrics. I’m particularly fond of the classically-British ‘modern’ fonts of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Johnston&quot;&gt;Edward Johnston&lt;/a&gt; and the saucy &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Gill&quot;&gt;Eric Gill&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve used them far too often already. If I used them in my portfolio site as well, I’d start to look like a one-trick pony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H&amp;amp;FJ&lt;a href=&quot;http://qz.com/167993/frere-jones-is-suing-hoefler-for-his-half-of-the-worlds-preeminent-digital-type-foundry/&quot;&gt;(RIP)&lt;/a&gt;’s Gotham looked lovely, but I can’t help but feel it’s on fashion’s downward slope now. Far too many people are using it without thinking, and of course it carries a certain politicised air with it now, too (thanks, Obama!). So keeping with the geometric “o” theme, the next obvious choice was Futura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Retro futurism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say there is some elaborate over-arching theoretical underpinning to my choice of Futura, but the reality is more prosaic. Sure I could waffle on about the retro-futurist stylings of the “W”s and “M”s, and how they fit into the dialectics of 20th Century design praxis, but in truth it was simply next on the list of “things to try”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I saw my generously-margined headings set in Futura Bold I was smitten. Couple that with the not-too-shouty elegance of the all-caps italic, and I’d found the lynchpin for my design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Flawed Futura&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many others, I actually quite like Futura’s much-maligned question mark, for all it’s eccentric meanderings. There are, though, some very visible problems with the ParaType cut of the font (the one I use via &lt;a href=&quot;https://typekit.com/fonts/futura-pt&quot;&gt;Typekit&lt;/a&gt;), and quite possibly with the typface as a whole, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowercase “J” looks stylish and bizare in equal measure, and the semicolon is oddly top-heavy. In body copy the x-height is a tad lower than I find comfortable and the letter spacing after an apostrophe is massive. Not an issue in a programme that lets you kern, but an ugly cross to bear on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, all the apostrophes and quotation marks look the same. It’s all well and good training yourself to press &lt;code&gt;alt shift ]&lt;/code&gt; every time you want an apostrophe, but Futura renders such efforts irrelevant. How many different characters can you count in the following sentence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/articleImages/futuraGlyphsSmall.png&quot; alt=&quot;'‘’“”&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tough, eh?! It’s a little easier at larger sizes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/articleImages/futuraGlyphsLarge.png&quot; alt=&quot;'‘’“”&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s actually &lt;strong&gt;seven&lt;/strong&gt; discrete glyphs there. There &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; differences, which at large sizes are delightfully subtle and nuanced, but at anything less than 72pt they all blur into one…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A designer’s website is like a builder’s house; always the last to be finished.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog-cum-portfolio site of mine has been through a seemingly infinite number of variations. What you see in April 2014 is only the third full ‘theme’ to make it all the way into code and deployment, but if you count Illustrator mockups then the number of iterations trebles. Count paper sketches – even limiting yourself just to fully drawn out and wire-framed designs – and the total skyrockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell how long this current designs sticks around for, but it already feels like this version is a more substantial website than any of my previous attempts. Picking Futura and sticking with it, despite the issues and imperfections, has meant I’ve been able to turn my attention to the finer details: the little moments of interaction design, the negative space, and above all the &lt;strong&gt;content&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/futura-for-the-win</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/futura-for-the-win</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Simple is hard</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;“Simplify, simplfy!” we’re often told. Your service isn’t appealing to your customers? The answer’s simple: simplify! Your song isn’t connecting with your fanbase? Simplify! You aren’t shifting as many units as Apple? Simplify! It’s an easy mantra to mock, and even easier to swallow hook, line, and sinker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we need to do is distinguish between ‘simple’ and ‘simplistic’. It’s fairly obvious that content suffers when overrun by crowded, cluttered, un-navigable interfaces. If what you’re saying has value, you don’t need the kitchen sink to help you say it. But what do you need? And how much can you afford to throw out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Only keep what you need.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deleting everything that you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; need only works when you know for sure what you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; need. It’s tempting to think of simplifying a design as merely stripping away layers of visual ornamentation, but true simplicity comes more from the &lt;em&gt;user experience&lt;/em&gt; than the look of the thing. Hiding an unsightly menu behind a &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobile.smashingmagazine.com/2012/10/08/the-semantic-responsive-design-navicon/&quot;&gt;hamburger icon&lt;/a&gt; is an easy way to de-clutter an app’s interface, for example, but does that count as simplification? All that achieves is forcing the user to make an extra click when they want to navigate somewhere. Even the &lt;a href=&quot;http://100archive.com/now/doing-the-hard-work-to-make-it-simple&quot;&gt;Government’s Digital team agree&lt;/a&gt; that this is both important &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; hard (and the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gov.uk&quot;&gt;gov.uk&lt;/a&gt; design is really impressive from a usability perspective).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearing away useless clutter is generally a good tactic, but there’s a distinct difference between &lt;em&gt;simplifying&lt;/em&gt; a product and merely making it’s function more obtuse. Is one button with five functions really better than five buttons that each do one task? Is an aesthetically-pure minimalist interface really ideal if you then need to teach every new user how it works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any task worth doing, there are many levels of nuance to simplification. It takes judgement; an assessment of what functions are important to your product, your app, your idea. Strip away anything extraneous and put anything the user needs front-and-centre, but don’t confuse the two or you’ll live to regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;This website is all about words.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The page you’re reading now went through many iterations before settling on the look you see today. Early drafts were swamped with full-page background images and clever CSS3 animation effects, but no matter how fancy I got with the coding these early designs never felt quite right. Then I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;http://justinjackson.ca/words.html&quot;&gt;Justin Jackson’s inspired ‘This Is A Web Page’ article&lt;/a&gt; and was reminded that what was important for this site was the words themselves. It goes deeper than that, even: what’s important to this site is the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt;. It could be read aloud by a screen-reader, translated into sign-language, even transmitted telepathically for all I care. As long as the message can be absorbed, this page will have done its job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I was doing with my early designs was trying to build a ‘great website’, when what I should really have been focusing on was building a great content delivery system. It seems video is the &lt;em&gt;de rigueur&lt;/em&gt; medium for getting messages across quickly, and for a while I did toy with the idea of making this page into a vlog, but ultimately words are purer. Video is harder to create than written content, and would skew the message with all the baggage brought along by seeing my face (beautiful) or hearing my accent (perfectly inflected Queen’s English). With the written word I have more chance of capturing the ‘white heat of inspiration’ and of being able to communicate my thoughts clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why use any styling at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why not go all-out and strip out all the styling from this page completely? Properly written semantic HTML is nothing &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; content, so surely stripping away everything else would be the most efficient way to get the message across? Well, quite frankly, the default styling applied by web browsers is &lt;em&gt;ugly&lt;/em&gt;, and that’s not as shallow a complaint as you might think. Concepts like line-height, line-length, leading &amp;amp; kerning each have a huge impact on the readability of text. To trust all those to the random whims of a browser is madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s often said that &lt;a href=&quot;http://alistapart.com/article/on-web-typography#section3&quot;&gt;we read best what we read most&lt;/a&gt;, and my what my friends and I read most are &lt;em&gt;books&lt;/em&gt;. Books are fantastically efficient, and the best ones are things of beauty that wrap their content in a nourishing blanket of aesthetic proportions and finely-wrought typefaces. Given how many books I own solely on the topic of type design and typography, I can’t stand idly by and leave my content at the mercy of the ‘web-safe’ default fonts. I have to believe that good typography and good design makes the reading experience better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Simple doesn’t have to be ugly.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems obvious, but websites &lt;strong&gt;still&lt;/strong&gt; have a lot to learn from books. Just because we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; swamp everything in technical wizardry doesn’t mean we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;, but it equally doesn’t mean we should abandon design altogether. ‘Simple’ doesn’t (and &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt;) mean ‘ugly’, and the simple act of thinking about line-lengths and visual hierarchies can turn an indigestible splurge of HTML into something readable, and in the right hands even something beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the right balance between visual simplicity, simplicity of interaction and a pleasing aesthetic is a real challenge, and I’ll be the first to admit I’ve still a long way to go. But at least now I’m pointing in the right direction; simple is important, simple is necessary, and simple is really hard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/simple-is-hard</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/simple-is-hard</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>A bullet-journal workflow</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Making task lists can be fantastically useful, but it’s all too easy to loose them. My paper lists get buried under reams of doodles and random notes, or lost in the depths of a full notebook that simply has &lt;em&gt;too much in it&lt;/em&gt;. Even digital lists get lost, and I find I lack the discipline to open a mammoth text file every morning. Paper is much better for immediate reference, even if it is easy to miss-place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Productivity Hacking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quest for elegant ‘productivity hacks’ is both fantastically useful and fantastically counter-productive. You can waste days reading about how not to waste your time. Finally, however, it seems that all the hours I’ve spent reading about productivity-hacks weren’t wasted after all; my current system finds me being &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; efficient and productive than I’ve ever been before. And at the hub of my new-found momentum lies my Bullet Journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Bullet Journal Concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devised by inspired Brooklynite &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rydercarroll.com/&quot;&gt;Ryder Carrol&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&quot;&gt;Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt; is little more than a seemingly-simple method of writing out a ‘to-do’ list using a pen and a notebook. I’ve experimented with similar list-hierarchies in the past, with mixed results, and while this new one is elegant, it’s not exactly revolutionary. But there’s one aspect of the Bullet Journal system that I’ve found to be a real revelation: the way the list rolls-over from day-to-day and month-to-month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What first drew me to the Bullet Journal was the systematized nature of its bullet-point organization, but what’s &lt;em&gt;kept&lt;/em&gt; me using it is the way it stays relevant.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Simplicity.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love simplicity, and the system itself is fairly straightforward – each list item is marked with either a square, circle or mid-dot. The square boxes denote tasks, circles events, and dots are standard notes (things to remember, but not explicitly actionable). At the start of every month I draw up a list of long-term goals, and then each morning I set out my daily tasks. I number the pages as I go, and keep an index at the front of the notebook. This makes assessing progress on long-term goals a piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;There’s only ever one active list.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of every day I write out a new daily list. Any items unchecked from the day before are either struck-through (which denotes they’ve become irrelevant) or marked with an arrow and copied into the new daily list. This way you never have to refer back to old lists hidden in the depths of the notebook, and it’s painfully obvious when a task is being continually put-off (which forces you to act: either do it or mark it as irrelevant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;There’s still long-term structure.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there’s only the one active list for you to deal with at any one time, the monthly lists are useful for reference, making it harder for day-to-day tasks to swamp your ‘big picture’ aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It’s flexible.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bullet Journal system is loose enough that it never gets in the way of my day-to-day workflow. If i need a date-agnostic list on a specific topic, I just make it and add the page number to the index. Little additions like this make the whole process expandable and fairly all-encompassing, and the day-to-day running of the list is never disturbed by all these additions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It’s really easy.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the journal up to date sounds like rather an onerous task, what with all the indexing, page-numbering, and three-tiered bullet system. In reality, keeping on top of all my lists is no hassle at all. Updating the list takes about 10 minutes every morning, and up to half-an-hour on the first day of every month (as I update my calendar, and re-set my long-term goals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/photos/journal02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My Bullet Journal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The journal isn’t &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; responsible for my productivity upswing, but it’s definitely helped.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By way of a disclaimer, making the switch to a Bullet Journal workflow wasn’t the only change I’ve made recently. A few months ago I quit my day-job and struck out on my own; an intrepid freelancer &lt;em&gt;cum&lt;/em&gt; entrepreneur bound for riches and glory! So now that any-and-all money that I make is directly proportional to how much work I do, it’ll come as no surprise that I’m working harder and longer than ever before (and would be with or without the Bullet Journal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&quot;&gt;Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; undeniably helped my workflow. My days now have structure, and (most importantly) I’m now much less likely to overlook an important task.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>http://tomhazledine.com/bullet-journal-workflow</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://tomhazledine.com/bullet-journal-workflow</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>